<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition vppon the thirtie two psalme describing the true manner of humbling and raising vppe of Gods children. Set foorth by Maister David Blak.</title>
            <author>Blake, David, fl. 1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118251</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853459</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853459</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18842</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16199)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18842)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 875:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition vppon the thirtie two psalme describing the true manner of humbling and raising vppe of Gods children. Set foorth by Maister David Blak.</title>
                  <author>Blake, David, fl. 1600.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Walde-graue, printer to the Kings Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At the foot of the title page: Cum priuilegio Regio.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXXII --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18842:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18842:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXPOSITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vppon the thirtie two Pſalme, deſcribing the true ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of humbling and raiſing vppe of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p>Set foorth by Maiſter <hi>DAVID BLAK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH</hi> Printed by Robert Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de-graue, Printer to the Kings Maieſtie. 1600.</p>
            <p>Cum Privilegio Regio.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18842:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18842:2"/>
            <head>AN EXPOSITION VP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the thirtie two Pſalme, deſcribing the true maner of humbling and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vp of Gods children.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Pſalme of Dauid to giue inſtruction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Pſalme hath this title common vnto it, with diuerſe others; ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe firſt the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and then the end. The author was <hi>Dauid,</hi> which is called in the Scriptures, <hi>The ſweete ſinger of Iſraell:</hi> who although he was a King, yet abuſed not his proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to ſpend his time in dalliance, and in the workes of pride; as many do when God hath advanced them; but beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe houres which might be ſpared from his politick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſultations, in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Pſalms, for the exerciſe of his faith,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18842:3"/> &amp; the edifying of the Church, wherin it is to be feared, that his example ſhal giue ſentence againſt manie wanton nobles of this worlde, who abuſe and diſgrace the worthie facultie of Poetrie, with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane Sonnettes, to ſatisfie their louſe mindes with a kinde of contemplatiue fornication, abandoning their good wittes, (which God hath giuen them) by writing of Pamphlettes, in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Cupid,</hi> which one day will be coumpted no better then ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſacrifices to the Deuil. We are taught therfor, if we haue any vein of verſifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or any other good vſe of our veine, how to vſe it, that by this example, our writings may ſauour of godlineſſe to ſtirre vp the mindes of others, aſwell as our ſelues therunto, not to leaue vnchaſt ditties behinde vs (as it were bawdes in the world) as many haue done.</p>
               <p>The end of the Pſalme is, <hi>to giue inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> that is to ſay, to teach others by his owne example, in a particular thing, whereof he maketh me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion. Now this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18842:3"/> inſtruction, as appeareth in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Pſalme, proceeded not from judgement gotten by much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and obſeruation of others, but by inwarde experience and obſeruations of GOD his dealing with himſelfe, which in the end of his laboures and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonies, hee recompteth and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to writing; which appeareth by many other Pſalmes to haue bene his vſual manner. So this inſtruction hath that ſinguler commendation, that it was deliuered out of the feeling of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> heart, that our ſpirites might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by his: as one face aunſwereth to another in water; which kinde of teaching, if not onely, yet for the moſt part and principally is availeable, either to humble when a man ſpeaketh not of ſpirituall things, as of the inhabitable ones (if any ſuch be) but as of thinges which he himſelfe felt &amp; taſted before. And this is that holy experience, which taught the high Prieſtes of the Iewes compaſſion, and made his offrings for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18842:4"/> his brethren more zealous; becauſe he felt himſelfe alſo pertaker of their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, as the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth: but now a daies, it may be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt the cauſes, why the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie of many ſucceedeth not better, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they faile in this poynt; in vſing ſo little conſcience in teaching the people, and being without all affections: But thoſe that are Rhetorical and prompted by the mother-witte, not by any expert ſoule, whereby it commeth to paſſe, that a godlie man, of no mouth or lippes, as <hi>Moyſes</hi> calleth himſelfe, that is nothing furniſhed with eloquence &amp; vtterance, ſhall build more ſound worke in Gods Church in one ſermone, then thoſe prophane Orators in twentie; though they haue neuer ſo great a facilitie in vtterance, and ſweete louſe of their words, as many ſenſeles men haue. Wee are therefore to make ſome profite of this, if we will be wiſe admoniſhers of others; that we labour firſt our ſelues to be ſpirituall men, that we may diſcerne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18842:4"/> al things, that we may obſerue how God hath wrought for vs in the like caſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; that both we may leaue behinde vs a ſting in the conſciences of others, and be ſafe guydes in ſuch a labyrinth, as a troubled minde is oft to bee led through. The maiſter of a ſhippe which is ignorant of the Seas, what skill ſoeuer he haue in Aſtronomie (which thing yet is neceſſary for Nauigation) whileſt he gazeth vpon the ſtarres, or any other artificiall direction, wracketh his ſhip vppon ſome rock, lurking vnder the waues, which would not bee, if experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had made him heedfull by ſayling that way before. And indeed, this intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable defect neuer ſheweth it ſelfe more ſhamefullie, or with greater hurt, then when men haue neede of ſpiritual comforte, at the houre of death; or in time of great affliction: for at ſuch times thoſe fooliſh ſheep-heardes, when they want skill to help their poore ſheep out of the ditch, are driuen to play the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable comforters, and to take ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18842:5"/> indirect courſe (as many vſe to doe in ſuch caſe) to cut the ſheeps throate in time, to make him mans meate, leaſt it ſhould be ſaid he died in a ditch: And theſe are the miſerable and deſperate calamities of the people prouided for, when they neede moſt of all ſpirituall inſtruction. And here we may eſpye the cauſe why manie admoniſhers and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructers of others, become ſo ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, as to be made the jeſting-ſtocks of ſinners; becauſe they admoniſh not, nor inſtruct not of feeling, weakning the power of their inſtructiones; if not by hypocriſie, yet by flatnes and dulnes of Spirite, that it cannot be receiued with that reuerence, that admonitions &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes wrought in the Primitiue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of the Church, when men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing touched home, fell vpon their faces, worſhipped God; affirming that God of a trueth was in thoſe miniſters. I might be aſhamed in a diuine exerciſe, to make mention of a Paganes counſel, eſpeciallie in ſo ſpiritual a poynt as this:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18842:5"/> ſaue that we are not aſhamed to let the Heathen get grounde in that wherein our Idiottes ought to excell their Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers; if thou wilt reproue (ſay they) conſidder firſt, if the ſame fault be not in thy ſelfe, or at leaſt ſome other, as ill or worſe, that the reformation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may be a foundation whereon to build thy brothers amendement. And indeed, although it is vntrue to affirme, that a man may not reprehend the fault which he hath in himſelfe; yet where men are carried head-long into an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage againſt other mens ſinne, without deteſtation or feeling any remorſe for their owne; It is very ſure, that in ſuch a man dwelleth that ſpirit of hypocriſie, which is the fowleſt furie of hell. Let vs haue therefore in our reprehenſions, whether publik or priuat, to our friends or to enemies, the ſpirite of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and invocation; that our wordes may haue grace with the hearers: For if before euery reprehenſion (if it were poſſible) and before euery inſtruction,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18842:6"/> we did lift vp our minds in ſome briefe meditation, commending the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our ſelues, and that preſent offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, both at once to God, and then proceede to a louing cenſure, as occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on requireth, our ſinceritie, our graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; our charitie would ſo adorne the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke, that the offender would rather be rauiſhed with the admiration of Gods grace in vs, then eyther ſcoffe it or grow into a choler, as many doe. But for-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as to men of a quiet nature, which hate the reproch of a buſie bodie, the deutie of inſtruction &amp; admoniſhing of others, ſeemeth an harder impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then they are willing to beare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is not one amongſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, that will take it in good part. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth therefore, that to that purpoſe we gather this third inſtruction from this title: namely, that men muſt make Gods proceedings with their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, profitable for the edifying of others, giuing them inſtructions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, as here we ſee <hi>Dauid</hi> doth: For it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18842:6"/> is the nature of faith to open mens mouthes, and to labour to make manie pertakers of their conuerſion. That loue which followeth true repentance, is neyther baſhfull nor fearefull, nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious, nor partiall: for when a man hath once got a good conſcience, all the reſt of his life after he ſpendeth in the inſtruction of others. <hi>Peter</hi> being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, muſt ſtrengthen his brethren; <hi>Dauid</hi> being forgiuen, muſt turne ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to God. I will ſay more, <hi>Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netzar</hi> being reſtored, publiſhed the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God to the Heathen: Nay, I will yet ſay more, the woman of <hi>Samaria;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but a woman, yet being reproued of her adulteries, &amp; inſtructed by chriſt; I will not ſay preached, but ſaith to her neighbours, <hi>Come, ſee a man that tolde me all that euer I did.</hi> And if her inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be Chronicled in the Goſpell to her commendation, ſurely the double ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and vncharitable quietneſſe of thoſe that will not meddle with other mennes matters, to inſtruct them when
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18842:7"/> occaſion is offered in matters of ſo great weight, muſt beare a note of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and be marked with the blacke coale of crueltie, and of ſoule-murther, for what is it els when we ſay, let them anſwere for themſelues, we will not put our fingers in the fire for them: as if <hi>Cain</hi> had not murthered his brother <hi>Abell,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaid, <hi>What? am I my brothers kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi> If we loue God, the ſame ſpirit is in vs, which was in <hi>Dauid, Mine eyes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>guſheth out with teares, becauſe men keep not thy commandments;</hi> If we loue men, the thread of our affection muſt be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by our care to inſtruct them, and wee will ſaue ſome by plucking them out of the fire with feare; and if we loue neyther God nor men, ſo that neyther the diſhonour of the head, nor the hurt of the member will touch vs; it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we our ſelfes are members of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other bodie, and not of Chriſt which is the head of his Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:18842:7"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>PSALM 32.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>1</bibl> Bleſſed is he which is lifted vp from his falling away, and whoſe ſinne is coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>2</bibl> Bleſſed is the man vnto whome the Lord imputeth not iniquitie, &amp; in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HItherto of the title; Now follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the PSALME it ſelfe, whoſe principall queſtion is, that there is no quietneſſe of conſcience, nor forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes; where there is no ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere confeſſion of the ſame: which DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VID proueth by his owne example, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming vs thereby; that as he, ſo long as he helde his peace, and concealed his ſinne, could not be ridde of the horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſenſe of Gods wrath: No more can anie of vs; how-ſo-euer otherwiſe wee trauaile in conuerſion as hee did: If we be ſowred with the leauen of like hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie. And to the ende that wee ſhould not be ſecure in the ratifying of a good conſcience, or make light of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18842:8"/> ſpyſes of diſpayre which are in vs, when we haue no attonement with God by the feeling of forgiuenes; he ſets downe the contrarie effects of a conſcience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged by Gods grace, and cheared vp with the remiſſion of ſinnes, and of the hearte, fraughted with diſpayre, and tormented with the terrour of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, becauſe it feeleth not the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of adoption. The firſt is ſet downe in theſe wordes; <hi>Bleſſed is that man which is lifted vp from his falling away:</hi> Here the Prophet ſayeth, that when God lifteth vp his children from their ſinnes, and aſſureth their conſciences of his loue, he maketh them bleſſed: whereout wee learne, that this indeed is that ſoueraign good, and high felicitie, yea the higheſt and only happines which can be enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this life, to be diſcharged of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill conſcience, tormented with the guilt of wickedneſſe, and fearing ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance for the ſame. By this effect he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth al of vs, as it were with a price to runne cheerefully, &amp; labour ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18842:8"/> for a good conſcience. There is no doubt, but that vngodlie men doe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times holde in admiration, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie and free eſtate, of godlie and vertuous men, when they ſee them ſtande vnmoueable as mounte Sion, when heauen and earth are mingled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: becauſe they themſelues haue manie ſecret ſtings, and are often ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed at the hart, who in worldly reſpects haue leſſe cauſe to feare then the ſheepe of Chriſts flock. Thoſe therefore which reioyce not thus in the heart, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they rejoyce in the face, muſt attend vnto this miniſtry of grace: For to what purpoſe doth the Lord open mens eyes to ſee the ſweet &amp; bleſſed eſtate of ſuch as haue humbled themſelues to walke with God, their confidence ſtanding before God, their rich hope, their quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and hartes-eaſe, their joy, as if they had one foote in heauen alreadie: I ſay, to what purpoſe doth God lift them vp, &amp; let them ſee the riches of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but to ſet their teeth an edge at
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18842:9"/> it, &amp; to rauiſh them with a deſire of the like; ſo then we ſee, that the Lord ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an offer of his grace vnto vs, &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſeth vs by theſe examples; that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forwarde if we profite not thereby, our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation might be imputed to our ſelues. Let vs therefore accompt this a meruellous happines, to feele ſuch a conuerſion in our ſoules, that in ſteede of our former miſerie, we ſhal perceaue our ſelues tranſlated from bondage to libertie, from death to life; yea, from hel to heauen: for he that hath a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, hath ouer-come the worlde by his faith. If Princes loue him, it ſhal not puffe him vp more then a pennie giuen to him, which is worth a thouſande pound; if they hate him and perſecute him, it ſhall not terrifie him, nor endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger him, no more then the great rebelles of <hi>Babell,</hi> endangered the heauen with their towre: For his ſoule is mounted vp aboue al theſe things, &amp; diſpiſeth them from an high. As for the vndermining of <hi>Sathan,</hi> who biddeth him ſpiritual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18842:9"/> combattes; they exerciſe him but they vexe him not; they make him actiue, but they deſtroy him not; his force is like the face of a Lyon, &amp; what-ſo-euer objecteth it ſelf, he beareth it down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; as we ſee a notable example (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t were) of a ſpiritual challenge of al the creatures of God, by S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 Where he caſteth down his gauntlet, &amp; biddeth a defiance to diuels, to men, <hi>to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ight, to depth; to things preſent &amp; things to come.</hi> And when we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider theſe things; how truly may we ſay, that the children of God, ſpiritually conſidered, are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Kinges and Emperours, Queenes &amp; Empreſſes, enriched with ſuch vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble bleſſings, that if all the harts of the world were one hart, it could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eine them. And as for them which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inue in ſin, harden their harts, &amp; by clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of wickednes, doe twiſt a roape for their own necks; how miſerable is their eſtate, when they behold this happines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n others, whereto they cannot atteyne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o pine away &amp; periſh in the beholding
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18842:10"/> of other menes ſaluation. And thus much of the effect which the feeling of remiſſione of ſinnes worketh. That which followeth of lifting vp from ſinnes, and not imputing them, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering them, commendeth vnto vs the grace of God, in beſtowing this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and ſealing the aſſurance of the ſame in our hearts, as the cauſe of the foreſaid effect, deſcribed figuratiuelie by the metaphors of lifting, imputation and couering: Al which, haue their ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall weight and importance in this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. Lifting vp from defection, argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth plainely a contrarietie in the eſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of man before, conſidering him lyein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a long in the contagious filth of his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſinne; ſo weakned, &amp; ſoaked cleane ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of heart, with the execrable leproſie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vngodlineſſe, that he is neyther able t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtirre hand or foote, till God lift him v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from his apoſtaſie. The word imputat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on is borrowed from accomptes, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuating, that we are run ſo farre in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rerages with God, that we can haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:18842:10"/> ſecuritie of conſciences, till wee haue gotten ſuch a releaſe, as may deliuer vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom all feare of imputation of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebtes, leaſt payment ſhould be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed of vs <hi>to the vtter-moſt farthing:</hi> as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in the Goſpel. Finally, the tranſlation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f couering or hiding of ſinne, is taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom a generall cuſtome of diſpatching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe thinges out of the way, whereof a man cannot ſuſteine the ſight, without greevance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moleſtation; thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, that ſinne is ſuch an eye-ſore to God, that he cannot behold it, and ſpare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t but at once; but that the deuil wil pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent it to God, and prouoke him to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſh it, except it be hid &amp; buried in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ottome of the Sea: and except the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ender be couered with the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt. So that in ſum, theſe words doe ſet downe the feebleneſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he pouertie and nakednes of ſin, which doth ſo diſcomfort him, if his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be awake; that till he haue founde remedie for each of them, hee thinketh himſelfe not out of the compas, where
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18842:11"/> fire and brimſtone ſhall fall, nor can be deliuered from a fearefull expectation of Gods curſe.</p>
               <p>And on the contrarie part; when hee feeleth himſelfe comforted by God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> right hande, and lifted vppe out of the quag-mire of contagious pollutions, hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſoule beginneth to <hi>taſte how ſweete th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lord is:</hi> and when he feeleth the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie of his debtes, which was grauen in his conſcience, cancelled, and ſo riuete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to CHRISTS croſſe, that they ſhal neuer be imputed; he drinketh a more hartie draught of the waters of life: but moſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all, when hee is aſſured that his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is ſo hidde, that it cannot preſſe to Gods throne for vengeance; nor riſe vppe in judgement againſt him, in the daye of his viſitation; hee is then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, and perfectlie bleſſed, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing that can bee added in this life, to the abſoluing of moſt perfit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> felicitie.</p>
               <p>This forcible propounding therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of this cauſe of bleſſedneſſe, hath in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18842:11"/> an excluſiue nature: ſecretly affirming, that there is no other cauſe of juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo of true bleſſedneſſe: But this grace onely, to the end that men might be ſtirred vp to take this courſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Holie Ghoſt is the guide. All men agree in this, that they woulde faine bee bleſſed: But there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent amongſt men, neyther in the cauſes, nor in the thing it ſelfe. The Philoſophers, for want of judgement, euerie one ſhotte his Bolt diuerſlie, and euerie one wyde of the marke, as appeareth in the collection, which CI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERO hath made of their opinions in his <hi>Tuſculane</hi> queſtions. The carnall chriſtan hath a true contemplation &amp; judgment, what is that <hi>Summum bonum,</hi> that is, chiefe happineſſe, but by the halting of an euill conſcience, hee is turned out of the waye; ſo, although he ſaye, it is in Heauen, yet hee ſeeketh it in Hell; though hee aſcribe it to the Spirite, yet hee laboureth for it in the fleſhe, (it is fearefull that I will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18842:12"/> ſpeak) though he acknowledge that it is the gift of God; yet he runneth after the deuill to obteyne it; which is then committed, when men thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues happie and bleſſed, if they can get riches, beautie, authoritie, ſtrength, life, &amp; ſuch others; which are common to the Reprobates. What can be ſo ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, as to heare the continual decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of worldly men againſt theſe vanities? And on the contrarie part; to behold the homage and frailtie; yea the ſlauerie in which they abandoned to ſerue ſuch vile thinges. If <hi>Dauid</hi> be well conſidered, it will not be eaſie to finde out many Peeres to him in worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes: His ſtrength is commended by the conqueſt of a Lyon, his courage in quailing of <hi>Goliath;</hi> his beautie is ſet forth with the praiſe of a ſanguine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, and amiable countenance: the paſſing ripeneſſe of his witte is manifeſt in all his ſtorie; &amp; touching his aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; God tooke his ſhep-hooke from him, and deliuered a Scepter; and after
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18842:12"/> his baniſhment, ſet him in the throne of his maiſter, which he poſſeſſed not by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſurpation; but (as it were) by a general election, that the heauens wrought with the applauſe of the people: His ſubjects were the onely men of the world; for the rare parts wherewith they were for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he moſt quallified; his Lande flowing with milk and honie; the temperature of the aire, incomparable withall other benefites, belonging eyther to health, profite, or delectation: with ſo large a hand, as if God had deuiſed to pleaſure him; and nature had mean't to emptie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll her riches into his boſome, and to continue the ſame by the plentiful hope of his poſteritie. Right truelie might I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aye, that this was a perfect picture of worldlie felicitie; and yet we ſee, that DAVID leaueth all this, and ſeeketh an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>her cauſe of bleſſedneſſe: for the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whereof, theſe thinges before did not help at all; teaching vs, that the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are ought to poſſeſſe our hearts, leaſt they be fore-ſtalled with a fond aſſiance,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18842:13"/> of finding honie in a hiue, where ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is nothing but waſpes, &amp; of imagining our ſelues to haue attayned to bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; when indeed we are as vnhappie a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> infelicity: becauſe we lye along not lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted vp from our ſins, which one day ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be imputed to vs; nor hauing our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes couered, that it ſhould not infec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ayre, nor offende Gods ſenſes, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dead carcaſe aboue the ground.</p>
               <p>Hytherto hath bin ſpoken of the cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of bleſſednes, which is the free grace o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, in remitting our ſins; the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances wherof haue alſo bene touched The laſt member of this verſe, which re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maineth, <hi>In whoſe ſpirit ther is no guyle;</hi> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth down a neceſſary effect of the ſame teaching an infallible rule to diſcern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> betuixt a preſumptuous &amp; falſe opinio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of remiſſion, and a certaine perſuaſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the ſame: that is, if there be no guy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the ſpirite; whereby it is vnderſtoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a ſanctification following forgiue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and joyned to true repentance; tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there remaineth no more couert dealin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:18842:13"/> to cloake our ſins in whole or in part, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare of worldly ſhame, or to ſeeke ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing holes to runne from God: but that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he mind wel perſwaded of Gods loue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndued with an honorable opinion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Church; thinketh it no diſcredit at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l, to make knowen to the vttermoſt, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir infirmities &amp; offences to God in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecret, &amp; to the church publikly; ſo far as the rule of edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Gods diſcipline <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>equire; as wee ſee two notable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les in this Prophet, and his Son; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the one hath left to the churh, the 51 <hi>Pſal.</hi> The other, the booke called <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>es;</hi> as publik monuments and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rances of their falls, &amp; liberal confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame; to remaine as it were on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he file, euen to all poſterities; ſhewing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herby their zealiouſnes in repentance, &amp; their ſincerity, in that they were not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ender ouer their credites, in reſpect of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the church. This then is the effect of that grace which forgiueth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndeed; neuer to ſeperate the gift of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes, from the gift of ſanctification
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18842:14"/> and the ſpeciall poynts thereof, which here is inforced; is through guyle of Spirite; to keepe back nothing vn-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, which the nature of true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance would diſcouer: But this is not al, for generall ſanctification is here ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the foot-ſtep of the holy Ghoſt, by the printe, whereof, we may knowe whether wee haue our portion in this grace of remiſſion of ſinnes, or whether the fearefull ſignes of the wrath of God abide vpon vs ſtill or no. Saint PAV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the eight to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> ſetteth downe the ſame doctrine, ſaying; <hi>Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> calling juſtification, &amp; ſanctification,</hi> are ſo inſeperable, that who-ſo-euer hath the one, hath the other alſo. And to TIMO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THIE (he ſayeth) <hi>If any man call on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> name of the Lord, let him depart from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie:</hi> Wherefore, it is the perfection o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> madnes, for a man that remayneth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, to dreame of forgiueneſſe, and when an hypocrite is pure in his own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conceipt, &amp; yet is not waſhed from hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſinnes. It is to true, that in thoſe that are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18842:14"/> regenerate, and are indeede forgiuen, there ſhal remaine ſuch a waſte and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauorie taſte, as ſhall much annoy them, and hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the relliſh or gift, euen of their moſt ſanctified actions: ſo that the Lord had neede to looke with a mercifull and for bearing eye, vppon the higheſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of his children; yea, they ſhall not be freed from the foule ſinne of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie; but ſhall feele with much vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, themſelues to be peſtered with ſuch thinges: how-be-it, in ſubſtance and in the chiefeſt drift of their life, they are true-harted to God; ſlipping into theſe former faultes by infirmitie, or by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſcanter meaſure of mortification, then they ought to haue laboured vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: ſo that the ods, is in the thing which is propounded to a mans deſire; for if his chiefeſt care in the loue and feare of God, be to ſeeke his ſaluation; what-ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer his hypocriſie be, it is not his guilt of ſpirit: But if he propound to himſelf ſome other thing, that his hart doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther labour for, then for ſaluation; it is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18842:15"/> certayne that hee is falſe-hearted to GOD, and that ſuch an hypocriſie is ane authentick recorde, of a man that abideth in his ſinnes: and ſuch a man as this, hath neyther faith to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-come the worlde, nor grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt temptation, and though he ſay, that hee is perſwaded of remiſſion, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll the mercie of GOD aboue the skyes; yet that guile that remayneth in his ſpirite, tormenteth his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence euery daye, conuincing him by this, that becauſe hee is not ſanctified, therefore he is not pardoned. For in this worke, there is neyther water one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor bloud onely, but both water and bloud, as Saint IOHN witneſſeth. It ſtandeth vs therefore in hande, not to ſatisfie our ſelues with a deuotion mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentanie; but let our mindes ſtande bent in holy wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes, not to bragge of the death of CHRIST, that it hath purged our olde ſinnes: But to feele how mightie it is to ſubdue the newe, that the ſinewes of vngodlineſſe in our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18842:15"/> hartes, and vnrighteouſneſſe and vnſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber behauiour in the out-warde man, may bee cutte off; For it is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of our election, if this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie bee in vs: Neyther doth the ſinne more certainelie diſcerne the day from the night, then this Spirite doth diſcerne him, which is accepted with GOD, from a wretch; whome he repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth; as Saint PAVLL plainelie ſayeth: <hi>If any man hath not the Spirite of Chriſt, the ſame is not of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>3</bibl> When I held my tongue, my bones conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med whileſt I waited all the day long.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>4</bibl> For thine hand is heauy vpon me day and night, &amp; my moyſture is turned into the drought of ſommer, Selah.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Hitherto the prophet hath declared that there is no true felicity where ther is no ſanctified feeling of remiſſion. Now it remaineth, that hee prooue the ſame which he doth by his owne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, declaring the greate anguiſh and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which he felt in his conſcience, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the waſting &amp; ſoaking out of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18842:16"/> ſtrength of his body ſo long as God hid his face from him, &amp; left him deſtitute of the hope of ſaluation, the cauſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he declareth in the firſt wordes of the verſe to haue bin, becauſe <hi>he held his peace</hi> that is denied to make a liberall confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his ſins, refuſing no ſhame not other abaſement what-ſo-euer belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereto, whereinto the holy Ghoſte reacheth vs, that cloking of ſin, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ſerueth for an excuſe in the world and ſaueth our credite amoungſt men: Yet it keepeth his conſcience vpon the racke, and maketh the arrowhead of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to ranckle in his bowels, whereto the ſaying of SALOMON agreeth in that 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. of PROVERBS, <hi>That he vvhich hideth his ſinne ſhall not proſper, but hee vvhich confeſſeth them, and leaueth them, ſhall finde mercie.</hi> But this ſentence before we proceede further, if it reſpecteth confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to be made to God onely, and not to the Church, hath neede of expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For if DAVID might haue bin relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the torments which hee heere
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18842:16"/> ſpeaketh of, with a ſecret confeſſion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, all other witneſſes being remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſo that no diſcredit might redound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o him thereby, it ſeemeth ſtrange, that he would abide ſuch troubles the ſpace of an houre, and would not rather gette him into ſome ſecret place, &amp; in moſte ample manner confeſſe all the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that he could remember, that he had committed euer in his life. The holie Ghoſt therfore in this place, by DAVID his ſilence, intendeth ſome greater crime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt him, then that he was dainty of his words, &amp; refuſed with his tongue to make confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto God; for it is certain that a domme man may make as accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table a confeſſion, as he that can ſpeake, but DAVID in this place accuſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of hypocriſie, and hardnes of heart, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n this, that he refuſed to deale ſeriouſly with his owne conſcience, and to perſiſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the meditation of mortification, till ſuch time as he had a ſufficient ſight and deteſtation of his ſinne, without which, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the confeſſion of men muſt be hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18842:17"/> &amp; their ſmoake infect the ayre. This then indeed was <hi>Dauids</hi> ſilence, that he refuſed to giue anſwere to the holy Ghoſt calling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his conſcience, &amp; for want of faith was kept either with ſome preſumption, or elles with ſome terrour from entring into a moſt graue conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and reſolute determination, to take ſuch perfite notiſe of the haynouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his ſinnes, as the nature of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance doth require: for this is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to vs all, that although we deſire to be ſaved, yet there is not one amongſt an hundreth that will taske himſelfe ſo zealouſlie, as hee ought with a ſincere perſeuerance in humbling himſelfe to walke with God; yea, and leaſt any man ſhould reſolue with himſelfe, not to bee ſtripped of ſackcloth, and aſhes, nor to put away the purpoſe of ſorrowe, and lamentation, <hi>in ſeeking after his vvelbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued</hi> (as it is in the ſong of SALOMON) <hi>till he had found her.</hi> The diuel hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected the heartes of many men with a damnable errour in the definition o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18842:17"/> repentaunce, making them beleeue, that, euery terror of the heart for ſinne, is the nature of true repentaunce, and to that purpoſe hee abuſeth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that CHRIST will not <hi>quench the ſmoking flaxe, nor breake the bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed reede.</hi> And by theſe fallacions and falſe comfortes, he quencheth the zeale of many, and maketh them giue ouer their laboure and conſultationes of humbling them-ſelues and ſeeking of CHRIST, before their conſcience haue felt any comfort at all. As if euerie ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row were godly ſorrow, or as if it were poſſible for mercie to bee founde and yet neuer felt, or for repentance to bee ſeparated from faith, and the ſpirite of fredome. This curſed diſcontinuance of our trauel in Godly ſorrow, the Prophet ESAY derideth, calling <hi>pennance for a daye, and bowing downe the head lik a Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſh.</hi> And the Prophet AMOS likeneth it, <hi>to the dewe and the Morning cloude which is ſuddainelie gone,</hi> And this is the <hi>ſwept and garniſhed houſe,</hi> mentioned
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18842:18"/> by CHRIST, <hi>Repoſſeſſed by ſeuen wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſpirites then before:</hi> For as this falſe repentance, feedeth their hearte with falſe hope, and ſuffereth not true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to take place; as appeareth in the daye of viſitation: So may this negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, &amp; giuing ouer our labour in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, bee worthelie accompted the cauſe, why men wallow in fowler enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities then before, ſwallowing againe, (as S. PETER ſayth) <hi>The vomite which before they had caſt;</hi> as it is moſt certaine and true: thoſe men finde in themſelues leſſe power to doe well; and are carried with more raging affections to do wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedlie, then euer they felt before. What ſhall wee ſay then? Do we require ſuch a meaſure of ſorrow, as might counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weight the ſame; or do we eſteeme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, by the dignitie of repentance? nothing leſſe: For we know, that if wee had a thouſand eyes, it were too little to weepe them out all, becauſe of our ſins: yea, if we had a thouſand hearts, though they al burſt with ſorrow becauſe of our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18842:18"/> tranſgreſſions; yet it were not this, but Chriſtes hearte bloud, that could make the fathers heart to yearne; or could me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite remiſſion at his handes; what is it then that we require? namely, that men returne not from the ſchoole of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to worldly delights, which <hi>quench the ſpirite,</hi> till their hartes bee made joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full by the holy Ghoſte, by feeling an heartie deteſtation of their wickedneſſe, and a reſolute determination to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue cherefully in the courſe of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſo long, vntill both faith &amp; hope be aboliſhed, that then reſting from their laboures, they may ſolace themſelues with loue celeſtial, as ſainct PAVLE ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth; for the trueth is, that manie when they compare themſelues with DAVID &amp; other of Gods children, I meane the difficulties and long afflictions of them, and the ſhort worke which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelus haue made, &amp; ſo eaſiely diſpatched in this worke of repentance, haue cauſe to ſuſpect themſelues vehementlie, and to examine themſelues ſtraightlie, by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18842:19"/> the fruites of feeling, and converſion, whether they haue right repented or no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sainct PAVL in the 2. Epiſtle to the <hi>Cor.</hi> the 7. Cap. like a man of experience, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe ſeuen notable affectes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; I woulde they were well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſed, that wee might trye our ſelues by them, for it is a care that ought to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe all the powers both of bodie and ſoule; conſiddering that Sathan with this engine, maketh a number of ſoules pertakers of their owne condemnation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The matter therefore groweth to this poynt, that although we confeſſe neuer ſo abſolutelie, that we are ſinners, with the greateſt vehemency of ſpeach that can bee, yet ſo long as there remayneth ſelfe-loue in vs, prevailing ſo farre with vs, as to make vs take exceptions againſt the ſeueritie of this ſpirituall diſcipline al this while; becauſe we cannot finde in our heartes to plucke out our eyes and cutte off our handes, at Chriſtes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandemente: that is, to deale ſeuerelie with our ſelues in mortifying euery pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18842:19"/> to offence: wee doe but flatter our breath in the winde, and the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſe that is in vs drowneth the ſounde of our confeſſion, ſo as <hi>A voyce cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e heard,</hi> as the Prophet ESAY witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. Let vs therfore as we are aduiſed in the REVELATION, <hi>be zealous in repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ance,</hi> that the holy Ghoſte may aſſure our conſcience, that our mourning is growen into the nature of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, not deceauing our ſelues with beginninges, becauſe the Scripture ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth plainely, that the proceedinges of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rue convert, is not to ſtay himſelfe with a perſwaſion of repentance, when hee <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s pricked at the hearte;</hi> but to ſteppe yet further, to lay holde vpon repentance it ſelfe, as vpon a more excellent and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ible grace; as we may reade, that it befel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o PETERS auditorie, in that 2. of the ACTES, of whom the holy Ghoſte ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, firſt, <hi>That they vvere pricked in their heartes;</hi> which leaſt it ſhould be taken for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epentance, he ſayeth, that vpon further <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſtruction, and more carefull ſearche,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18842:20"/> they atteyned to repentance it ſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, that we may knowe, that <hi>prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the heart,</hi> &amp; repentance are not all one, but two ſeuerall thinges, whereof one may be in a loſt child, as that was in IVDAS, but the other belongeth oneli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the ſons and daughters of God. Thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath DAVID declared how he brought himſelfe into fearefull troubles, (as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were) by gagging of his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, leaſt he ſhould make ſuch a confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as it required at his handes.</p>
               <p>Now it remaineth to be conſidere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what troubles thoſe were. <hi>My bones ſait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he, conſumed and waxed olde, &amp;c.</hi> That is care which eateth out the hearte, mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her impreſſione in my body, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoughts which I had taken, did ſo pyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me away, that it burneth the marrow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out of my bones, &amp; drieth vp my youth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full humours with penſiuenes (as it ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beene with olde age) which he repea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth in the next verſe in other wordes ſaying, <hi>That the hand of God vvas ſo he</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>vpon him day and night, that it ſpent his n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18842:20"/> and turned the beſt moyſture vvithin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> into the drought of ſommer;</hi> as if it had beene entering into the moſt incurable conſumption of all otheres, when that which is called, <hi>humidum radicale,</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to ſpende. Theſe ſpeeches are vſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o teach vs into what plight, concealing of ſinne bringeth men, and we are the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inforced, that we ſhould not thinke that theſe clowdes would bee ſo eaſilie ouer-blowne, as thoſe miſeries which proceed of worldly cauſes. Marke then, what wee haue to learne in this place, what is the eſtate of them which be not in league with God, if wee looke vpon them with a worldly eye; I confeſſe wee ſhal ſee many of them with their breaſts full of milke, &amp; their bones full of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe: <hi>yea they haue collopes in their flankes,</hi> (as IOB ſaieth) but if we look vpon their conditione with a ſpirituall eye, wee ſhal wel perceaue, that their conſcience as often as their preſumptione is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, is nothing-els but an hell, and themſelues ſo terified with the horrible
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18842:21"/> ſtiching thereof, that it worketh the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more woe nor all their worldlie peace i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worth: for ſuch is the eſtate of men no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reconciled to God, <hi>That the ſound of fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is neuer out of their eares,</hi> (as wee reade i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> IOB,) and this is the cauſe why theſe men cannot ſuſtaine to heare the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God againſt ſin, becauſe they thinke themſelues all the while to be ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rained at Gods barre; for where there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no truce with God, the law goareth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſcience, and the ſoule thinketh i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe tormented before the time: and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this be ſo, how greate is the hardnes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe mens heartes? and how monſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rous is their cruelty to their own ſoules<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which can ſhake of the care of reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, &amp; can rejoyce with a Sardini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an laughter in ſinne, when the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bendeth his browes againſt them. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, we haue here an ample teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the frowardnes of our nature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which will not be reclamed without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame dealing; for DAVID himſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (you ſee) is layde vpon the racke, and al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18842:21"/> ſtreached a ſunder, euerie ioynte one from another, before hee can bee brought to a ſincere confeſſion, ſuch a work hath the Lord with vs before hee can make anie grace to growe in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eartes, which ought to teache vs theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wo thinges. Firſt, that we enter into an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eartie miſlike of our ſelues, and to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rieuouſly diſpleaſed with our vntracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lenes, which compelleth God <hi>to heare vs vp, and caſt vs downe againſt the ground;</hi> (As DAVID elles where ſaieth,) and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fflict many ſo ſore, that (God his ſecret grace excepted) they ſeeme otherwiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n reſpect of the maruelous afflictions which God is driuen to lay vpon them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be ſhackled foote to foote, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>robate and deſperate perſons: all this I ſay) proceeding, not of cruelty or fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the Lorde, but of our owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ractablenes (who otherwiſe coulde not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſſibly be ſaued) ſhould make vs to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perpetual warre with our affections, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd to conceaue a preſent hatred, as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere, even of our ſelues: for if the Lorde
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18842:22"/> might eſpie that in vs, that wee woulde <hi>Iudge our ſelues,</hi> hee woulde not bee our judge, but our comforter in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict. The next thinge that wee haue to learne, is to judge wiſely of the afflicted ſoule, &amp; to beware how wee condemn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> anie, becauſe the hand of God is terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vpon them, for the text ſaith, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen DAVID himſelfe, who had conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſome former ſincerity, and wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> able to ſubdue manie aſſaultes, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in knowledge, yet was he eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brought to the brinke of diſpaire, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was tormented with an horrible fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of damnation: euen as it is vſuall with God to exerciſe his children with thoſe tryalls, no otherwiſe, nor if he whippe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them with Scorpions. The worldly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men, which neuer were tranſlated from death to life, being ignorant of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpirituall miracles; in calling; morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, regenerating, and chaſtening o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his children, when they ſee a man in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perplexitie; they ſay hee is madde, me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lancholious &amp; deſperat, increaſing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:18842:22"/> griefes of the afflicted, with bitter tantes &amp; mockes; which is to be feared, many one day wil rue it. It ſtandeth vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in hand, to expel ſuch vncharitable conceipts; knowing that the deareſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, may be wonderfullie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed and racked with exceeding and long torments of conſcience; yea, many times their ſayle is rent in peeces; their tackles, and all their tackling burſt; their bruiſed bark left to the wilde waters &amp; the winde; and yet for al that, at the laſt they obteyne a ſafe aryval to the ſhore. Let vs then, for the concluſion of this poynt (if any ſuch thing be fall vs) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware to lay any vn-reaſonable thing to Gods charge; yea, rather let vs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his mercie; who, when he might haue puniſhed our long and tedious hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, with hardneſſe of heart; chooſe rather to put himſelfe to all that payne, to reclayme vs by correction, that wee might take heede to our ſores, how wee ſuffer them to runne long cured on the out-ſide, but feſtering within; knowing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18842:23"/> that by theſe meanes, we ſhall put our ſelues to greater paynes at the laſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can bee cured: how-be-it, for that which is paſt, and cannot be reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; let vs not be diſmayed with this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, from ſubmitting our ſelues to the mightie hande of GOD, <hi>For hee is a faithfull keeper of ſoules, and will not ſuffer them to bee tempted, aboue</hi> (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or) <hi>their power.</hi> Thus hauing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the effect of DAVID his ſilence, we are to giue heed to a ſpecial circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which he ſetteth downe in theſe words, that <hi>He roared all the day long.</hi> Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying thereby, that his praiers ſo long as they were not mixed with faith, nor ſeaſoned with true repentance, were no better then <hi>roaring:</hi> That is, then the crying or bellowing of ſome bruitiſh &amp; vn-reaſonable creature. For this is a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphore, taken from Lyons, taken in a ſnare, or being in ſome other diſtreſſe, as appeareth in the third chapter of <hi>Amos,</hi> and in other places, where the worde is vſed in his proper ſignification; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18842:23"/> we learne, what difference there is, betwixt the prayers of the faithfull, and of them which nowriſh fraud &amp; deceit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n their ſpirit: The ſacrifice of the one is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>indled from heauen, &amp; when he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oured out his ſpirite, he hath eaſed his hearte; hauing caſt his burthen and care <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herof vpon the ſhoulders of CHRIST: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut the hypocrite, in the day of viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, fareth like a beaſt that is ſticked or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aled with ropes, wanting all reaſon &amp; fore-caſt to helpe it ſelfe: and therefore vſeth no meekneſſe nor entreatie, but with roaring and ſtrugling, ſtrayneth it ſelfe, and tangleth it ſelfe more; &amp; with bruitiſh raging, doubleth the pain. There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s no doubt, but where great afflictions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight vppon men that are taynted with hypocriſie: the aire is beaten with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſuch roaringes, and men flutter like birdes in the net, when God hath caught <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem: but all thoſe ſenſeleſſe prayers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aile them nothing more, then if an Ox <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould break out of the ſlaughter-houſe, with the roape tied about his hornes, &amp;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18842:24"/> his toung hanging out, with much bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing and madneſſe, when hee had caught a knock with the axe. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may ſee the excellency of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prayers: Yea, the Angell of GOD doth aſcende vp in the ſmoke of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, whereas men that wil not yeeld, but will reteyne their ſins, cannot pray, but rage and roare deſperatlie, like Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Beares. Neuertheleſſe, it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs wiſelie to vnderſtand this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, that it concerneth hypocrites, and them that holde their falſhood in the right hande. I ſay, it belongeth to them, becauſe they haue not faith, nor conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in their prayers: For otherwiſe, it is certaine, that the moſt excellent chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of GOD, are many times ſo lowe brought, with the anguiſh of an afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted conſcience, that they cannot vtter anie perfite prayers with their lippes: but do ſpeake abruptlie halfe ſentences; yea, halfe wordes, being broken off with the extreamitie of their pangues that come betuixt; (As <hi>Ezechiah</hi> writeth of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18842:24"/> himſelfe) <hi>That he chattered like a Crane or</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Swallow, and mourned like a Doue.</hi> And there is no doubt, but all Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren doe feele a ſtrife and a combate in their ſpirite, in many of their prayers; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en as we ſee green-wood lieth ſobbing and ſmoking long before it will burne: We are therefore to put a differance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene this and roaring; becauſe the Scriptures are full of examples of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfite ſpeaches in the prayers of Gods children: yea, in the praiers of CHRIST himſelfe; which commeth to paſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe manie of thoſe ſacrifices, are ſo ſeaſoned and peppered with ſalt, and with fire; yea, afflictions come ſo thick on Gods children, that they haue no time to ſwallow their ſpittle: But yet in them there is a ſweete ſenſe of Gods grace; and the Lorde inlargeth the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnder them; yea, he puts his owne arme betuixt them and the graue, that they ſhould not bruiſe themſelues with any fall; for although hee leaue ſome trouble of minde, yet hee looketh vpon
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18842:25"/> them through the chinkes of the doore, he hath compaſſion of their dolorous la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, <hi>and putteth all their teares into a bottel:</hi> For why, they haue yeelded vnto GOD, they haue kept nothing backe, and therefore can praye with a feeling ſpirite; whereas the hypocrite doth not pray, but roare; becauſe hee will not truſt God: For an euill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, doth ſtoppe his mouth, &amp; the ſins of his youth, are ſtill in his bones.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>5</bibl> Then I acknowledged my ſinne to thee, neyther hid I mine iniquitie; for I thought, I will confeſſe againſt my ſelfe my wickedneſſe vnto the Lord; and thou tookeſt away the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of my ſinne. <hi>Selath,.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then I acknowledged my ſinne, &amp;c.)</hi> Thus farre DAVID hath ſet forth by his owne example, the diſquietnes of them which hold their peace; and refuſe in ſimplicitie of heart, to make confeſſion of their ſinnes. Now on the contrarie part, hee ſheweth by his owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; what is the effect of Gods grace, when it hath brought men to godlie
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18842:25"/> humilitie, to reſolue to confeſſe their ſinnes to God, in that which followeth next. <hi>Then I acknowledge my ſinnes vnto thee, &amp;c.</hi> This diligence in deſcribing his confeſſion in ſo manie wordes, that hee would make knowne his ſin, &amp; woulde not hide iniquitie; but confeſſe his apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie vnto the Lorde; doth declare, that he hath gotten the victorie ouer all hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; and at the laſt, after long ſiege, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad gotten the hold of ſimplicitie, and ſinceritie: So as now, there remained no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urning, nor winding, nor extenuating of his ſinne, when hee had to doe with GOD, as there was before. As for the Lorde, he is not hindered with anie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ediment of ignorance, or dulneſſe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhould not know by a word, what the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hole meaneth; yea, though he confeſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſinne at all; yet for his part he taketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erfite notice of all our offences with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut vs. It is not then for his ſake, that we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake anie confeſſion, as if we could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe him by our hypocriſie, for he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th through the darke cloudes: but it is for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18842:26"/> our owne ſakes; to the end; that compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our liues, with the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God; &amp; confeſſing how much wee ſwarue from that holie rule, wee might be ſtirred vp to great contrition, and might be more deepelie ſet in the meditation of our owne vnworthines, that being ſo humbled, Gods ſpirite might take occaſion to faſten vpon vs, and to lay ſure holde vpon our hearts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thus we ſee, that it is the nature of true confeſſion to aggrauate our ſinnes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging that confuſion of face be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to vs, and charging vppon our heades, the ſinnes of our ſelues, of our fathers and children, wiues, friends, and all others; ſo farre as our guiltineſſe may anie way ſtretch; not in any ſet or labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red phraſe of ſpeech, but from a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience nurtured with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bling, vnder the juſt hand of GOD: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this ſort, the Prophet calleth himſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>beaſt</hi> before God; And Saint PAVLL ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſeth himſelfe of <hi>blaſphemie</hi> befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his conuerſion, affirming, not with fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18842:26"/> humilitie: but euen as he thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n his heart, that he was the chiefeſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er amongſt them, whome CHRIST <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame to ſaue. And in the Primitiue Church, Saint PAVLL ſheweth, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umilitie was joyned to the confeſſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f them which were conuerted by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing the Prophecies, or exerciſes then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed; that they fell vpon their faces. As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndeede, if we be indued with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite of true repentance, we can finde in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur heartes to humble our ſelues, euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elow to the ground: &amp; the verie cauſe why ſinners make it ſo ſtrange, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſpirit of pride hath ſtil the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſion of their hearts; which euil ſpirit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt be caſt out of vs, befor we can mak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nie ſuch confeſſion, as God will accept <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f at our hands. There is another thing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich the holie Ghoſt ſetteth downe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be marked in this place; namely, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he children of God haue a joyfull iſſue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f all their temptations, that the Lorde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill bring ſome excellent thing to paſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the laſt; by afflicting his, which is their
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18842:27"/> mortification and ſanctification: Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this is the end of all his hewing, to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them <hi>liuing ſtones</hi> fit to his Church, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſorting to the <hi>chiefe corner ſtone, which</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>our Lorde</hi> IESVS CHRIST; to whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mage by this meanes we are confo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med. If the Lorde had brought all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worlde vnto captiuitie vnder DAVID yet, if hypocriſie had reſted in his hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it had bene all accurſed to him: but no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that the Lorde hath renewed a right ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite in him, both heauen and earth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſanctified to his vſe: But aboue all, he hath gotten the libertie of conſcienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſingeth with a joyfull note: <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> haſt taken away the puniſhment of my ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> This is al in al, that his ſoule is refreſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the feeling of remiſſion; and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſoone as the Lorde ſaw him willin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to judge himſelfe, he ſteppeth from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tribunal ſeat, to the bar; &amp; of his judge becommeth his Advocat, to pleade fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him; taking away the puniſhment of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſinne, which being ſo; who is he, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wilbe affrayd to deale ſeuerlie with hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:18842:27"/> ſelfe, to call his conſcience to a recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, that he might repent him ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of his ſinne? Who ſhall blaſpheme his way any more? calling it the waye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f deſperation, ſince we ſee the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie in the example of DAVID; who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſo telleth vs elſe where, <hi>That with God is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ercie, that he might be feared:</hi> Whereto, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aint IOHN alſo agreeth, denying that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ee haue anie ſuch cauſe to dread diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aire: <hi>For if wee acknowledge our ſinnes</hi> ſayth he) he will not take vs at the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge, and condemne vs out of our owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>outhes, <hi>but hee is faithfull and iuſt, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rgiue vs our ſinnes, and cleanſe vs from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l vnrighteouſneſſe:</hi> Yea, many times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od chideth and comforteth both at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne inſtant: as we may ſee in the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le of the woman of <hi>Syropheniſſe;</hi> who, if hee had bene terrified, with the ſharpe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>buke of CHRIST, ſhe had loſt her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bour, and the commendation of her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith.</p>
               <p>At the end of this verſe, &amp; the former, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſetteth this word <hi>Selah;</hi> which is a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18842:28"/> note of attention, ſtaying the meditatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> longer vpon theſe two ſentences, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon the reſt; declaring therby his judg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, that both theſe his contrarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, are worthie of obſerving, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they afflicted his heart exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. Whereout we learne, that we ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not to paſſe by Gods proceedings, with a conſcience blinde-fold; nor careleſlie to paſſe-ouer, the ſtrange things that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reade, in the ſecret book of our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: but when-ſo-euer wee hitte vpon ſuch notable experiences, to turne in a leafe there; to marke it with a <hi>Selah,</hi> and to peruſe it ouer againe and againe, that we might get ſome holie experiences in matters of conſcience; for this is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> manner of Gods ſeruants, to bee cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the eſtate of their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; that they may knowe what kinde of Phiſick will beſte agree with them: For default whereof, wee ſee manie mens conſciences by their owne confeſſion, to haue ſurfeted often of the ſame thinges; and to haue eſcaped the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18842:28"/> frute of many heauenly motions, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f they had bene receiued, might haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urniſhed them with much riches of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odlie meditations. And indeed, this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he cauſe why the <hi>Pſalter</hi> is more diuine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or all the reſt of the Bible; becauſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen the Lorde had ſpoken once, DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ID heard him twiſe; and all the way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s he marched, he ſet downe the geſtes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd circumſtances of euerie dayes jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey in a Commentarie; ſo that his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erience, committed to the godlie me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orie, made him to excell in the ſight, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth of Angels and men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>6</bibl> Therefore ſhall euerie one that is godlie,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake his praier vnto thee, in a time when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ou maieſt be founde; ſurelie in the floud of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea: waters, they ſhall not come neare thee.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>This farre reacheth the firſt part of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Pſalme,</hi> propounding that generall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>octrine; that ſincere confeſſion to God neceſſary for the quieting of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ience; without which, it is impoſſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> attayne the peace of God, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ling of forgiueneſſe in the hearte, as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18842:29"/> DAVID hath made it plaine by his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> experience, on both the ſides. Now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the ſeconde parte of the <hi>Pſalm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> which is the application of the ſaid doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, conteining in it a declaration o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the deuties, which men are to be ſtyrred vp vnto thereby; wherof, the one is ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and faithfull prayer; and the other is quiet and peaceable obedience to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> calling of God; and the ſaid application beginneth thus; <hi>Therefore ſhall euery o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> that is godlie, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here the Prophet DAVID inferret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a conſequent, vpon the mercie which God ſhewed him, when he had ſhaken of all hypocriſie, and had gone directly to the matter; that eyther men ſhould be prouoked to godlineſſe, by the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereof, for there is no other end why the infirmities of the Patriarcke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Prophets are ſet downe in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <hi>But for our comfort and inſtruction,</hi> (as Saint PAVLL ſayeth) It is ſure, that profane men, as they peruert the vſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all things, ſo do they abuſe all thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18842:29"/> as if it were ſome excuſe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers &amp; drunkards; to mention the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alles of DAVID and LOT; whereas in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem the Lord hath declared the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of the beſt, when God with-draweth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ſpirite, and that no ſuch ſinne is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ardonable; if men will returne as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id; as it muſt be a great incouragement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o preſent our ſelues before God, when we ſee how wel others haue ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore vs: There is none example in al the Scriptures, of any that euer ſped euill, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y confeſſing his ſinne to the Lorde, what-ſo-euer the ſinne were: For there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s not any ſinne, but ſome of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ren haue fallen into it; ſo it hath bene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he caſe before<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and wee may be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aged by their example, to wade out as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey did: Yea, we ſhall finde more caſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y their experience: for euen as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich firſt ſayled in the Seas, gaue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er names to dangerous rockes, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lous places, where they hardlie eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed with their liues; to the end, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſteritie by ſuch marks, might ſhunne
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18842:30"/> ſhip-wrack, and paſſe ſafelie away; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſuch places diuerſly, as the Sage-bed, the Lavender-bed, with other like names beſt knowne to Saylers; and as Carters vſe to ſet vp ſome buſh or other like mark in that place, wher their waine ſtack faſt, for a warning to them that come after: ſo haue the godlie Fathers furthered vs, by their experience, and taught vs to eſchew many encombran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which they (becauſe they break the Ice firſt themſelues) could not ſee: and this obſeruation in the ſtorie of IOB, commendeth his faith exceedinglie, for he ſeemed to haue dwelt far from Gods people; and to haue bene deſtitute in ſo great affliction of all theſe incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes; ſo that if life and ſoule had not bin kept together, by reſtoratiues of the holie Ghoſtes owne compounding, he might haue deſpaired a thouſand times. It may bee, hee had read the bookes of MOYSES; but yet that was nothing, in compariſon of the comfortes, which wee may haue: Therefore, let vs lay vp
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18842:30"/> this leſſon in our hearts, that although God ſhould carry vs away into <hi>Tartaria,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o that in ſickneſſe of our conſcience: wee could haue neyther Preacher nor friendes preſent with vs, to miniſter ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall comfort: It ſhould ſuffice vs, that we haue the aduiſe and example of the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles; though parents, wiues, children, bee a thouſande miles from vs, and all other acquaintance: for what a glorious viſitation of the ſick is that, when wee haue Patriarches, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, Confeſſors; yea, and CHRIST himſelfe, ſtanding rounde about the bed; comforting and chearing vs vp: If wee ſay wee be ſick at the hearte, becauſe wee haue liued ryo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſlie and venterouſlie; hee that was the prodigall childe, taketh the taill by the ende, and ſheweth how he himſelfe once labored of the ſame deſeaſe, but now is cleane ridde of all the dregges of that ſickneſſe. If the patient replie and ſay that his ſikneſſe is a reciduation (as the Phiſitions calleth it) &amp; that he hath
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18842:31"/> fallen into it againe, ſince his profeſſion of religion: The Prophet DAVID aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth him fullie to that matter, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that his ſicknes anſwereth in that circumſtance, to a ſoare maladie of his owne: For I alſo (ſayeth DAVID,) was a principall profeſſour, before I committed theſe two moſt horrible crymes, as all the worlde knoweth: But my diſeaſe (ſaieth the patient) is olde, and of long continuance (yea and I ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth DAVID) played the hypocrite a year. If he haue beene a perſecutor of the Church, PAVL comforteth him; If hee haue denied CHRIST, though it were with perjurie; PETER ſteppeth forth &amp; ſheweth his own example; finally, they all direct him to the Phiſition which ſtandeth by, feeling his pulſe, (for they were all cured by one doctour) adviſing him to giue over himſelfe to be ordered by him, and the ſame is IESVS CHRIST. Now if in the ſicknes of the ſoule there be ſo manie viſitors of ſuch ſundrie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, all reaſon doth exact by their
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18842:31"/> example, that therefore euerie faythful man do pray vnto God in his aduerſitie to be made partaker of the like remedy.</p>
               <p>Now it followeth that wee ſee whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herto DAVID doth exhort men in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pplication, and that is firſt to the deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of prayer, ſaying, <hi>Therefore ſhall euery faithfull man praye vnto thee:</hi> eſpecially he aymeth at that parte of prayer which is ſpoken of in his own example; to wit, confeſſion: In place wherof he puts this generall word, which comprehendeth all kinde of ſupplications, wherein wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ske, confeſſe, thanke, or praiſe God for any thing, teaching vs by this aduiſe, the certaine comfort which is to bee found in true prayer, that it is the towre of the faithful, wherein they continue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues when the enimie aſſaulteth them; even as God appoynted them in the 50. Pſal. Telling vs that when we are <hi>in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wee ſhall call vppon him, and hee will deliuer vs,</hi> and SALOMON in the dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Temple, deſireth God that the ſame effect be giuen to prayer, which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18842:32"/> is here ſpoken of, <hi>That the flouds of waters may not come neare;</hi> that is, when men are in peril &amp; terror, if they confes their ſins and make their ſupplications to God he would deliuer them, as indeed ther is no other ſo direct means, whereby to haue acceſſe to God as prayer, neither doth God make anſwere out of the heauen to any thing that we prefer to him ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly as to praier; for he delighteth in the ſoule of that ſacrifice more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in al other. And therefore the Angels are ſaid to be employed in carying vp the praiers of ſaincts, as if God had preferred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more in aſſigning them that office then in any other thing, &amp; the excellency hereof is commended in this alſo, that wheras di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other vertues may be outwardlye performed by thoſe that ar ſtrangers to Gods couenant, though without ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity there was neuer any vouchſafed to conceaue three words of a faithful prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but if he be the vndoubted childe of God. Let vs then giue heed to this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, and wreſtle with our ſelues from
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18842:32"/> morning to night, to performe this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which done ſincerely in anie mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at all, ſhall do vs more good in our miſeries then all other remedies beſide. It is common to be ſene, when the hand of God is vpon men, <hi>That the waters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to come vppon them,</hi> they ſeeke after helpe, and ſuccour twenty wayes, but they are al worldly, and not able to giue them any comfort. As for prayer, becauſe they haue not vſed themſelues thereto, neither their memorie nor their skill doth ſerue them, but for want of faith and calling vpon Gods name, <hi>the floudes of greate vvaters burſteth in vpon them,</hi> and they periſh miſerablie. Yea, &amp; theſe examples are verie common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs in time of greate calamitie when men going out of the world, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be brought to any comfortable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this duty, but are feareful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y depriued of their ſoules, before they haue giuen anie comfortable markes of their fayth. There are manie which can conceiue the words of praier eloquent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18842:33"/> but the comfort is his onelie which can pray faithfully; and therefore our harts muſt be exerciſed therein, &amp; then our tongs ſhall be taught to pray more ſweetely vnto God, then if we had ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died our wits to ſet euery word in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: for euen as euery floriſher or fenſer proueth not a tall man when hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to fight in good earneſt; no more are thoſe prayers found effectuall, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can ſuch men ſpeake a word to the purpoſe when affliction hath laied hold on them indeed. When as a true chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian neuer ſheweth his manhoode, nor his cunning in this weapon of prayer, more then when hee is to fight for life and death, and the greater the daunger is, with ſo much the ſtouter courage is he indued. And that alſo is worthy the marking in this place, that in a calamitie which ſeemeth vncurable when the handes of worldly men do faynt, &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litickes ar at their wittes end, then there is ſuccour in prayer, and there is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in calling vppon the name of God,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18842:33"/> for though (ſayeth hee) <hi>that prayer ſhall turne away the flouds of greate waters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat although our troubles were as the ſea, vvhoſe violent courſe cannot bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rned, and whoſe mercileſſe waters can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſtopped, yet prayer maketh them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o flye back-warde,</hi> as it were againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; ſo that the raiging and vntamed flouds of greate waters dare not come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare. And how much doth this extoll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he excellent eſtate of Gods children, who ar furniſhed with remedies againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emedileſſe thinges, and with cures for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncurable woundes; euen as it is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ature of faith, not to boaſt it ſelfe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hinges that are ſeene (as the Apoſtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith) where there is no neede, but to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccupied about things inviſible and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſſible to the fleſhe. Saying,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>7</bibl> Thou art my ſecret place, thou preſerueſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e from trouble, thou compaſſeſt me about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith ioyfull deliuerance. Selah.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>In this next verſe, the Prophet ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth downe a ſhorte forme of prayer to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vſed of the faithful, wherein the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18842:34"/> is a petition to be preſerued i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miſery, on theſe wordes, <hi>keepe mee from diſtreſſe,</hi> or in the ſtrayt of my troubles; which is inforced firſt by an argument taken from their faith, which expecteth the inviſible grace and defence of God when all the world denieth ſuccor, <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> art my ſecrete place.</hi> Secondly, by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the ſaid deliuerance, that the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God ſhall be ſtirred vp to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond duty of prayer which is to praiſe and glorifie Gods name. <hi>Thou ſhalt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe me about with ſonges of thankes-giuing</hi> In the firſt where the faithfull are taught to call God, <hi>their ſecret place,</hi> is meant that they acknowledge the eſpecial car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God ouer ſuch as call rightlie vppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his name, that he is their refuge, &amp; dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſecretly, &amp; with grace (which the worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is not vouchſafed with the ſight of) pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tect and ſuſtaine his, ſo as they remain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſafe, when the world looketh that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhalbe ouer-whelmed with diſpaire an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> calamities. And this adminiſtration o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, doeth aſtoniſhe the worlde wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derfullie,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18842:34"/> when they ſee a poore ſillie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odie, who hath no abettor or mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyner, nor any man of countenance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o back him; but that he is like a lowe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edge, which euery man may ſtep ouer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot to bee diſmayde with all this, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>lay him downe</hi> (as DAVID ſayeth) <hi>and ſleepe</hi> in much ſecuritie, when his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nemies keepe ſtout watche and pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th their tentes againſt him; IOBS wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sketh ſuch a queſtion of her husband; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd that with muche indignation; <hi>Doeſt thou ſtill perſiſt in thine integritie?</hi> Thinking it abſurd, that he ſhould bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſtant in avouching the righteouſnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God; when there appeared no token, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut of his wrath and furie: Aſſuredly, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he confidence of men, which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue in worldlie munitions, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her meanes of ſafetie; are like the houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f a ſpyder, in compariſon of this: And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herefore, we ſee oftentimes, their Sun <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oeth downe at noone; but when God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>deth his children, vnder the lappe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s garment; neyther men nor diuells
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:18842:35"/> enemies ſhall not terrifie vs; but ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eyes being opened by prayer, ſhall be hold the mountaines over-ſpread wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Angels; and wee ſhall ſee, that whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they cannot diſcerne: namely, that <hi>ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are more with vs, than vvith them</hi> (as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Scripture ſayeth.)</p>
               <p>The next reaſon to mooue God t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaue his Children in their ſtraight; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that he may compaſſe them about wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſonges of thanks-giuing; that is, by de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uering them, he might miniſter occa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of his owne prayſes, as it is in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pſal. Open my lippes, and my mouthe ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſhew foorth thy praiſe.</hi> This as I ſaide, is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſecond part of prayer, where-unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> people were moued, vnder the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niall law, by ſtreight paying of vowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> leaſt the feare of God, ſhould be dim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed in them by proſperitie &amp; hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> caſe; whereby appeareth, that this du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of thanks-giuing, carefully perfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med, is a ſinguler exerciſe of faith; whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men ſtanding vpon the ſhoare, and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holding the dangerous &amp; tumultuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:18842:35"/> Seas, which they haue paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, are ſtirred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſacrifice prayſe and glorie to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame. And thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeruice the Lorde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth greately accept, and taketh much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> light in it; yea, it is a further worke of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ith, then petition, which is the former <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rte of prayer: for thoſe which are but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lightned againſt death, may ſerue in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t to make ſome petitions to God; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey neuer be-think them at all, of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tie of thanks-giuing, when they haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ued benefites of him: And for this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e nine of the leapers which <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d are defamed to all poſteritie by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e holy Ghoſt in the Goſpel: For there as nothing more odious nor this ſin; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d therefore God hath not ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t it to the cenſure of the Church, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th reſerued it to his owne judgment. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et vs then labour to purge our ſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch a wickedneſſe, ſpending much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our time, in the ſonges of thanks-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng, ſince God hath compaſſed vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ut with them, and hath giuen vs ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nie occ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſiones to prayſe his name.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18842:36"/> The book of the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> though it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt much of the firſt part of prayer, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be full of petitions: yet in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle, is called <hi>A Booke of prayſes,</hi> name<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the Church, as it were of the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> honorable part of prayer: and indeede ſuch hath bene the thankfulneſſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods children, that their loue canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> keepe within the bankes, but burſt fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into the prayſe of God, in the midde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of ſome other treatiſe, as wee may ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue in Saint PAVLL, in the firſt to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Romans</hi> verſe 25. To be briefe, the exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lencie of thanks-giuing, ſheweth it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> here in that, whereas men make petit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, it is of loue and care of themſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For the ſupplie eyther of ſpirituall o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bodily wantes, but where men offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thankes, it is of a kinde heart, of a louing and honorable affection, conceiued to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards God, when they ſtriue with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues, and are in a ſorte grieued, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they haue nothing worthie in them t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> render for all his louing kindneſſe: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that their loue cannot extend to him, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:18842:36"/> we reade in the 16. <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>8</bibl> I will inſtruct thee, and teach thee in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>y that thou ſhalt goe, and I will guide thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ith mine eye.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>9</bibl> Be ye not like a Horſe or like a Mule, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nderſtand not; whoſe mouthes thou doeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nde with bitte and bridle, leaſt they come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eere thee.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>10</bibl> Manie ſorrowes ſhall come to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>cked, but he that truſteth in the Lord, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> ſhall compaſſe him.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Hytherto reacheth the firſt parte of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he application, as touching the duetie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t Prayer: The ſecond parte followeth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſwading to obedience: For the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er performance whereof, the Prophet DAVID, turning himſelfe to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, promiſeth to be their guide therein: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd this his guidance (he ſaith) ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, firſt, in inſtructing them, &amp; adviſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem in the way wherin they ſhuld walk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> then in guiding them with his eye. By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he firſt, hee meaneth that he will teach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem out of the worde of God, the true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uties of obedience, according to his
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18842:37"/> Propheticall function, and the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of this dutie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſignifieth, by va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the ſame thinges with diuerſe Phraſes, that hee will bee painefull and plaine in teaching them, giuing ſuch manifeſt directions, as if the waye were chalked before them. Thus hee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth an argument to perſwade to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which indeede, in foldeth in it manye argumentes: That King DAVID, that Prophet of the Lorde, a man of ſingular experience in ſpirituall affaires would be their skoole-maiſter, &amp; that in moſt playn &amp; paineful maner, whereout we learne this doctrine: That when the Lord ſendeth fit inſtruments into the Church, which haue both skill and will, to feede it with handes of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, it ought to be an argument o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obedience, to all that haue a ſparkle of Gods grace. To this purpoſe, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Sant PAVLL putteth the <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in minde, that he had vſed ſuch dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and playnenes, in preaching the paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord, &amp; had done it ſo liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18842:37"/> as if indeed they had ſeene CHRIST IESVS crucified before their eyes, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the labour of the Prophetes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in this plaine manner, wrought nothing among the Iews: The Prophet ESAI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>cap.</hi> 18. denounceth Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt them; &amp; after, he ſheweth by two familiar compariſons, how they had bene inſtructed as Children, that learne the <hi>A. B. C.</hi> which name the letters after their skoole maiſter; and as they which haue their handes ledde, when they learne to write; which hee meaneth by theſe phraſes; <hi>that precep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ath bene vpon precept, and lyne vpon line.</hi> And herein they to whoſe charge it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppertayneth, are taught not to bee ſtamering or ſquemiſh, but like louing nurſes, to take all in good woorth, though they haue manie a foule hande with the rude people, euen as Saint PAVLL ſetteth himſelfe foorth for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n example, when hee ſayeth, that hee travelled againe with the GALATHIANS although one trauell is as much as a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18842:38"/> is able to beare for her own childe. I would we had learned well this leſſon, that ſuch as teach others, were not cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away with the ſpirit of nicenes, and vaine-glorie: ſo a greate parte of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, whether of a baſe opinion that they haue conceaued of Catechiſing; as too low a thing for their excellentnes or whether of anie irkſomneſſe to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell with the rude &amp; forgetfull people; or for what other cauſe I knowe not; whileſt they preach themſelues and let their owne geſtes take winde, leaue the people vninſtructed in the neceſſarie pointes of ſaluation, not leading them as they ought, <hi>in the waye wherein the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould walke.</hi> On the other ſide, the people in many places, though they haue this argument to moue them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; that is, a paynefull and godly paſtor, yet they are mooued hereby no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, but had rather haue ſuch an one as ſhould Propheſie no more vnto them in the name of the Lord, yea it is to be thought: that the number of good
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18842:38"/> teachers had bin greater if ſuch as loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>not inſtruction had not given the NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>RITES wine to drinke, they which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue none to inſtruct them, hope to be excuſed by ignorance, though vainelie, but to them which haue a teacher, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efuſeth admonitions, there remayneth neyther hope, nor excuſe, for euen the prayer of them which will not heare; <hi>ſhall be abhominable</hi> (ſayth SALOMON.)</p>
               <p>The next poynt is, <hi>that hee will guyde them with his eyes,</hi> which is more nor the former: for hee promiſeth not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with general exhortation to do what good hee can, but alſo to attend vppon them with his eyes, &amp; at every turne to helpe their wandering, and to goe in &amp; out before them himſelfe, which how well he performed in his ordinarie, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a king, and in extraordinary as he was a Prophet, the Scriptures giue am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple teſtimonie. This place teacheth vs, that the continual preſence of the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (neceſſitie onely excepted) is a forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meanes to bring men into obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18842:39"/> as may appeare both by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and by reaſon: for we know, that a friend of approued godlines and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whome we vſe familiarly, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whoſe boſome wee may emptie our ſecreetes, ſhall preuaile more with vs then any ſtranger whatſoeuer. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. PAVL forbiddeth the miniſter to beare himſelfe coylie and ſtately a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people, but to be gentle and eaſie to be ſpoken to, to the end that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance may winne loue, and loue may gaine obedience, and for this cauſe the people are compared to ſheepe; which knowe their owne ſhepheardes whiſtle, from all others by dayly vſe. It is certaine ynough, that wher the teacher neuer attendeth on his office; but in the pulpet; there the people ar ſheepe which feede in lowe places, at their own wills doe rot for want of a better ſhepheard. S. PAVL in his farwell ſermon to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians,</hi> layeth this example of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Miniſters, that hee had <hi>taught to the people houſe by houſe,</hi> and the ſame
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18842:39"/> Apoſtle ſheweth that the <hi>Leuites</hi> were maintained of the ALTAR vpon this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that they were reſident at the ſame. Thoſe therefore that are the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of IESVS CHRIST, their loue to him will moue them, the word of God will commaund them, the example of DAVID &amp; all good ouerſeers wil meete them, compaſſion of the people, and dreade to murther the ſoules which CHRIST hath purchaſed with his owne bloud, will provoke, inioyne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine them, <hi>With diligence to feede that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke vvhich dependeth vppon them.</hi> The temptations which draw a man from this duety are groſſe, and ſuch as euen the ſhame of the world might ſhift off: how much more ſhould Gods ſpirite prevaile againſt them; for the gaynes which is gotten by ſpirituall promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ioyned with ſpirituall diſtructions; is more ſhamefull and infamous, then the gaines of the vſurer or of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouter; yea it is the moſt odious &amp; bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous ſhifte that the diuel can deuiſe.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:18842:40"/>
               <p>BALAAMS bribe is called <hi>the wages o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> iniquitie;</hi> but this filthy lucre (I ſpeak a reprochfull thing) is the Hang-mans wages, for the loſſe of the precious liues and ſoules of men is their booty: But of this matter, the complaintes amongſt men are ſo manifold, and the ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to God for reformation are ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, that it ſeemeth fitter to expect what God will do, then to preach any longer to the bellie that hath no eares.</p>
               <p>This much hath beene ſpoken of the promiſe which DAVID maketh, to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and guyde the people;</hi> vſed by him as an argument to moue them to docili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and obedience. Now for aſmuch as the moſt parte when they are to bee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by good Diſcipline, doe fare like wilde creatures: he dehorteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the ſame, ſhewing what will bee the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of diſobedience, that it will bring a double paine vpon them, &amp; make them to haue a rougher and greater bitte in their mouthes; that is, they ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to yeelde to their griefe and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18842:40"/> payne, if they will not ſhew themſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>actable by faire meanes. But before he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eth this argument, he maketh the ſinne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vntractablenes odious, by comparing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with the brutiſhnes of <hi>horſes &amp; mules,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich are not well broken, who manie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mes ſeeke to miſchiefe their keepers; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a wilde horſe, if he cannot by kicking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d rearing caſt his ryder, watcheth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me til the rayne be ſlacked, &amp; getting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he bit betuixt his teeth, ſetteth his tayle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ende, and runneth his ryder againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he trees and walles, &amp; through hedges, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſpoyle him if it bee poſſible: &amp; when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e is downe giueth him a fare-well with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s heeles. As for the <hi>Mule</hi> ſhe is well y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough knowne to be a froward and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly beaſt; ſo that if her keeper watch hir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot the better, ſhe wil take him vp in her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eth; &amp; lay him before her in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. The Prophet therefore poynteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rth this ſinne of frowardneſſe, vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Images of an <hi>Horſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Mule,</hi> to note <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto vs, that there is nothing ſo bruitiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to reject, the doctrine and gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18842:41"/> which God hath appoynted fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our ſouls: wherof although ther be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Iudges, yet none can tel ſo wel, what a trouble-ſome peece of work this is, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the faithfull miniſters of the Goſpell, which are driuen to mannage ſuch reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and vntamed jades, as ar many amongſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the multitude, for what with yerking ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the heeles, riſing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hinder legs, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing ſide-long; &amp; other froward touche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of vnbroken coltes; the poore Miniſter if he be on their backes, can hardly keep the ſaddle; and if hee leade them in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hande, on frowarde jade or other in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pariſh, taketh him vp by the coller, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> throweth him out of the way; ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a man be neuer ſo honeſt, and haue ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie good friendes; yet if he will doe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dutie, hee ſhall hardlie be able to ſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> without ſuſpention or depriuation, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome ſuch like foyl; which would neue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come to paſſe, if it were not for the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Mules</hi> in his Pariſhe: and this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the cauſe, why many giue ouer the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good beginnings in their miniſtrie, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18842:41"/> their people are ſo tickle heeled: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; thus it commeth about, that the Lande is full of ſhiuen jades, which can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euer be broken of their vnhappie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erties, becauſe they were marred in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>andling at the firſt. Let vs then learne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot to miſlike or condemne the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of good Paſtors; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing the example of ten thouſande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich are negligent: For the Scripture ſayeth, <hi>that they are not buſie-bodies in ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing,</hi> but we are <hi>Horſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Mules</hi> in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>beying; as indeed it is evident ynough, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow ſauagely &amp; furiouſly many behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, in rejecting the nurture of the Goſpell; which other-wiſe, before the Deuill was interrupted in them, had the commendation of ciuill men, of court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, and courteous Gentle-men: The precepts of ciuilitie, &amp; the rules (as they call them) of vrbanitie, do teach a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o avoyde what-ſo euer is vndecent &amp; vnſightlie in geſture or phraſe, in looke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r gate; ſo that there are ſome to bee
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18842:42"/> found, ſo exactly framed to theſe things, as if they had bene caſte in the verie mould of ciuill behauiour. But alas, what profite is there in ſuch matters, when men for lack of chriſtian educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, notwithſtanding their ciuilitie doe diſgrace and diſcredite them-ſelues ſo much, that when the Goſpel is applyed, ſuch forgetfulnes of all good manners l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yeth hold on them, that they fome at the mouth, and take on like wild <hi>Horſes,</hi> that a man would wonder, what were become of all their courteous demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure, when they ſhew their teeth for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: &amp; I am perſwaded, that manie of them, who ſtand vpon their owne cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dites, if they could ſee their faces in a glaſſe, would hide their heades long after: yea, there is no more ſenſe nor witte, in ſuch malecontentes, then in them which kick the heele againſt a prick, as CHRIST told Saint PAVLL. This ſpeaketh DAVID, to make diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience an hateful thing vnto vs, becauſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18842:42"/> it transformeth men vnto bruite beaſts. He addeth (I ſay) this argument, <hi>whoſe mouthes with bit &amp; bridle</hi> thou muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine, <hi>leaſt they come near thee;</hi> ſhewing, that as <hi>Horſes</hi> get nothing by their mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; but the ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er <hi>bit and bridle;</hi> no more doe ſtubborne perſons get any thing by oppugning the Goſpell, <hi>For they wraſtle with God,</hi> (as SAMVEL ſayeth) And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, when wicked men take on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods worde, they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ridiculous, and wretched ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; becauſe they barke at the Moone, <hi>and he which ſitteth in the heauens, laugheth them to ſcorne:</hi> Wretched, becauſe they cruſh themſelues, by running againſt this rocke, and are deſperately bruiſed with this ſtone of offence; euen as wee ſee many of them which are enemies to Gods worde, with this bruiſe to ſpitte blood all their life after; that is, to giue evident tokens of a tormented conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: For there is nothing gotten by ſtruggling vnder Gods hands; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:18842:43"/> his owne children, when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come impatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his inciſion, are bound to a ſourme. For it is certaine, that Gods worde cannot giue place to men, &amp; the true miniſter of the Goſpell, will not be repu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed from his dutcy by Princes, to the hurte of a good conſcience; but the ſpirituall authoritie, in this miniſtration ſhalbe ſuch, that it ſhal ſuffice. <hi>To binde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Kings with chaines, and noble with ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Iron,</hi> (as ſome interpreth the place of the <hi>Pſalme</hi>) Wherefore, let vs judge righteous judgement, thinking nothing to be more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onorable nor to be maiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the worde; and nothing to bee more prejudiciall, then to ſhewe our ſelues wayward and from pole, in croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and reſiſting of the ſame.</p>
               <p>And thus the compariſon is finiſhed in this verſe; now the application of the ſame followeth in the next verſe, in theſe wordes, <hi>Manie ſorrowes ſhall come to the wicked &amp;c</hi> So that euerie thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put in his place, it is to bee diſpoſed
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18842:43"/> in this manner: as <hi>Horſes</hi> and <hi>Mules</hi> for their wildneſſe, do bring bittes and bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles vpon themſelues; ſo froward men, by their diſobedience, going on in their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnes, doe heape ſorrow on their owne heades: which is alſo declared by the contrarie, in the other member of the verſe. <hi>But he that truſteth in the Lord, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall compaſſe him about.</hi> And in this application, wee muſt haue an eye to the propoſition of the <hi>Pſalme,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diſcourſed of the ſinne of hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and how hardlie men are brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e the true remedies, that belong to the curing of an euil affected co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>rat doth he aime in this place alſo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ming, that men ſhall get nothing by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ng like wette Ecles out of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ndes, but ſhall double their owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>uble, by ſhifting and cloaking ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, when they haue to doe with God: For there is no miſchiefe like to this, when men finding themſelues diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the ſtraightneſſe of the gate
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18842:44"/> of grace, caſt about to finde other eaſier waies, imagining that a man may doe well ynough, though he lay no ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition vppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himſelfe, as the ſtrict doctrine of repentance doth require: For although the vanitie of mans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes be euident in manie things, yet it appeareth in nothing ſo hurtefull, as when men think they can finde another way of ſaluation, then that which is ſanctified by Gods worde; yea, this is wicked follie, which hath caſt men in diuerſe calamities, which thinke that they haue a reache beyond the Moone, both to ſuck ſtill of the breaſtes of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſſe, and yet to nouriſh the hope of ſaluation in them ſelues: while men ſtraine their wittes, to bring things to theſe tearmes, they bring the whole matter out of the ſockat, and diſturbe their owne conſciences, with much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnes; and a great deale more heart-byting, than they which neuer looke after ſaluation at all, by reaſon that they
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:18842:44"/> ſtriue to bring two ends together, that will neuer meete. And to this purpoſe, they reject what-ſo-euer is ſharper then aggreeth with their humour as ouer preciſe, and when they are taken in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ette with ſtruggling to get out, they intangle themſelues more and more, by perſiſting in ſtubbornes, they bring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie troubles vppon themſelues, vntill at the laſt they dye for verie anger, like Weeſels that are taken in a trap. Hereof King SAVLL is an enſample, who was readie to haue vſed manie ſhiftes by Witch-craft and other odde meanes, when he was vexed with an evil conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: But all his ſhiftes tended to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end (as things fell out,) but multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed his calamities and griefes, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he propounded co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort to himſelf. And ſo it is with all wicked men, to whome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t any aduerſitie happen, their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can make no conſtruction, that it is Gods louing viſitation, but his very curſe vpon them, &amp; he croſſeth them
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18842:45"/> in all their actions, feeding them with anguiſh and confuſion, as it were with bread, which play the hypocrites be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and diſtruſt his gentleneſſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they ſhould ſubmit themſelues to him without any condition: yea, the Lords eggerneſſe againſt ſuch men, is maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſlie deſcribed in the Scriptures, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> hee will make his dartes drunke with bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d, that he will ſpend all his arrowes vpon them, that he will be ſo hote in the perſute of them, that he will not ſo much as bayte in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but drink of the water of the brooke,</hi> as wee may ſee in his horrible judgements vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Aegypt: Who hampered PHA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and his people? neuer leauing them to long as hee could finde them warme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> For aſſuredly, as it is his firſt delight to do wel to his <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſo the very next is, to glorifie himſelfe in his juſtice, by multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the ſorrowes of the wicked, whereas on the contrarie part it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. <hi>Thoſe that truſt in the Lord, mercie ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l compaſſe them about, &amp;c.</hi> That is, they
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18842:45"/> giue themſelues into Gods handes, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nfayned confeſſion, keeping nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ek, but ſtanding contented to abide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> awarde whatſoeuer, becauſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dly truſt they repoſe in him, their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecration ſhal faile them no whit: For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Lord ſhal ſo gird them round about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th his mercies, and the ſence of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r, that no terrour ſhall aſſayle them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut for the multiplying of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the ende. And all the difficulties ſhall be ſo cleane remoued, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall finde the yoke ſweete and eaſie for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem, which galleth the neck of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tient diſſemblers: for when God is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>d he ſetteth ſtore of his credite, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th more for them that beleeue him: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> euer they expected, ſo that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me to be in a dreame rather then to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e poſſeſſed indeed with ſuch bleſſings, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e greatnes and aboundance of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>o incredible as in the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.4.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>11</bibl> Bee glad ye righteous, and reioyce in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Lord: and bee ioyfull all ye that bee vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18842:46"/> in heart.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The laſt verſe contayneth the efe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the free grace and mercie of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is felt in the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt, that it is a ſwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peace and vnſpeakeable joy of con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence, to the fruitione wherof he exhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth juſt and ſincere men, where by w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are taught, that the ende of Godlie l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours, and of the trauells of a penite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſoule, is as comfortable as the ende o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> SARAHS trauel, when ſhe was delivere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ISA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſonne of promiſe (the child of olde age) &amp; the hope of all the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> world. For ſo it ſhall come to paſſe wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them that faynt not that they ſhall no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be able to contayne the ſpirituall joy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and comfortes which ſhall rayne vppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them in a ſweete ſhowre from heau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> howbeit their joy is here limited, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they ſhould <hi>reioyce in the Lorde,</hi> whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt not bee counted any imparing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> joyes in Gods children, but an holy c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection, for want whereof they mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> poſſibly ſtretche forth their hand wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:18842:46"/> the wicked, and reape vnto themſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Image of joye in ſteade of true by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te: for that is the property of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly men, to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moue the diſcomforts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their heart, by worldly delectations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> called for Muſicke when hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oubled with an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uill Spirite, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o this purpoſe (men that be affrayed of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>paire, and loue not to be humbled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nder the mightie hand of God) doe vſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir wifes, their friends, their meate &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir drinke, with al the paſtime that can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e deuiſed, to rejoyce themſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, that they might put themſelues out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the dompes (as they cal it) But in ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſes none of theſe evills come vppon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e head of the righteous, but hee refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth all worldly ſolace, and will not bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ted, til he haue found the joy of conſcience, that hee may rejoyce in the Lorde for this is a ſure joy as CHRIST <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayeth, that <hi>no man can take away:</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s not ſo ſpoken, as if a man might not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue a joyfull vſe of Gods temporall
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18842:47"/> bleſſings; as of wife, of children, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> friendes and poſteritie, (&amp; ſuch things) but rather to teach vs how to rejoyc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rightly in thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things, conſidering tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there can bee no harmony, where th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chiefeſt ſtring of the inſtrument is mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing, which is a good conſcience, which referreth all thinges to God, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth there can bee no ſafe vſe of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thinges, but vnder the ſhaddowe of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> winges. Thoſe therefore that think tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> godlines is not fit for all thinges, for al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> times and places; but to be reſerued to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſome ſpeciall devotions, as if it were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable and vndiſcreete to mentio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it in the middle of their paſtimes an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> delightes, ſeeme to bee better acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſacrifices of the <hi>Indians</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with true godlines: for let vs aſſure o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſelues, when wee deſpiſe to haue o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtes ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nctified aſwell as our ſerious matte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, wee are playfellowes with the divell, who ſupplieth the ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> godlines is expelled, but ioyes thus ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18842:47"/> haue no releaſe in the mouthes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nbridled &amp; vntamed per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ink it a dead worlde if vnchaſte daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uffenly ſpeaches, and other ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>litie be reſtrayned, at feaſtes and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ges, and other merrie meetings: Yea, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>any olde people will ſay, that there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o ſetting of old mens heads on young <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ns ſhoulders, being as it were patrons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the vnbridled wantonnes of youth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen they rejoyce altogether without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Lorde. The ſonne which hangeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he head, and looketh like a ſheepe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſence of his father, bewrayeth a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yall, and ſeruile nature; and he which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>noweth not how to be chereful, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>epe his countenance amongſt his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rs: will paſſe all boundes of modeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>irth &amp; honeſty amongſt his equalles; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſo fareth it with them which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t be merrie, and wiſe in the Lorde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich hadde rather bee ſilent, then b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounde to the Lawe of grace, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue no certaine courſe except their
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18842:48"/> diſſolute byas be obſerued. Theſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> (I ſay) bewraie a ſlaviſh nature, becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they cannot tell how to bee mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>long as God is by them: I meane an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> godly reſtraynt, that the land-marke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vertue may not be remoued; &amp; vndo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tedly, as it is ſeene in this thing, ſo it is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the weighteſt buſines of the conſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence, for when Gods peace is not vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, all the jeſtes in the worlde canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mooue a man to laughte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> teeth outward: except the heart be ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dened, (which is an horrible thinge t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeake off) for himſelfe is the ſubſtanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of our ioye, and theſe worldly delectat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons are but circumſtances; in him alon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may we rejoyce though they all faile but without him they are all comfort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble as much as ſalt is for ſore eyes. Fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thermore, this exhortatione to appr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hend ſpiritual joye, is directed to juſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſincere men: that is, to thoſe that ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſet vp juſtice as a marke to ſhoote at, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue decreed to hold in the path of ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rity,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18842:48"/> though they be far from any me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>torious righteouſnes, ſo that this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce doth not allow the juſtice of men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t doth as it were <hi>the Cherubin</hi> by the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ee of life</hi> keep away with Gods ſword; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oſe that loue vnrighteouſnes and are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e harted, that they ſhould not ſtretch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rth their handes to gather the bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ite of this joye: for it is ſure ynough, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at there are manie as S. PAVL ſayeth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at rejoyce in the face, which rejoyce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t in the heart, nether ſhal they be able <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> get downe anie comfort, ſo long as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey loue ſinne more then God: no, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ough all the partes of their life be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rned with ſuch moralities, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rd works, as appeare not in many of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ods deare children: for the workes are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t the adjunctes of faith, but the loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d ſincerity of workes, for fayth will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vne her ſelf to nothing, which can be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Reprobate. And as hope and Faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e not of thinges viſible, no more is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>iſhment of hope &amp; faith by workes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18842:49"/> apparent, but the Lorde loueth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> plaine meaning ſoule, and filleth bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the handes thereof with comfort, fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> whence ſpringeth the vnſpeake-ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> riches of faith, and of hope; and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the ſcriptures maketh the heart th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeate of ſincerity, and not the brayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> becauſe the heart is the houſe of the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fections, and the brayne the ſeate o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Iudgement: For IVDAS knew CHRIS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his bloud to be innocent, but his hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was cruelly affected to his maiſter. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vs therefore bend our ſelues to ſtriue a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ſince<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ty and vprightneſſe, that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> may he gladded with the ſpirite of adoption; and that we may rejoyce not in the fleſh, but in the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18842:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
